Labor Schools for Women Workers Pamphlet Collection 5531
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Labor Schools for Women Workers Pamphlet Collection
1924-1945
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Aaron, Maxine L.
Bryn Mawr College
Bryn Mawr Summer School
Hudson Shore Labor School
Southern School for Workers
5531
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Pamphlets, publications.
Consist chiefly of correspondence and reports generated by the various workers' education schools of the Affiliated Summer Schoools for Workers. Materials generally pertain to the conduct of courses, fundraising and cooperative activities of the summer schools and the American Labor Education Service.
3336743
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 14, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 10, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Maxine L. Aaron collected these documents in the course of her service on the Pittsburgh committees of the Bryn Mawr Summer School, the Affiliated Summer Schools for Workers, and the Hudson Shore Labor School. She was also active on the Workers Education Advisory Committee of the Works Progress Administration's Pittsburgh workers education project.
Scope and Contents
Materials regarding the American Labor Education Service (ALES) include pamphlets, reports and notes on government support of workers' education programs, labor plays, music, women workers, unions and workers' education, workweek and wages, and activities of student workers. Also reading lists and bibliographies; brochures and pamphlets on courses and curricula offered at the various affiliated schools; an ALES scrapbook; and letters of the ALES staff to various unions and philanthropic organizations pertaining to finances and recruitment of staff and students (1928-1937).
Also materials regarding the Works Progress Administration's Pittsburgh workers' education project. These include minutes of the Workers Education Advisory Committee; memoranda, reports and letters on the training institute, communist instructors and administrators of the project, housing, curricula, fundraising, and union cooperation (1938-1940).
Additional materials include brochures, pamphlets, yearbooks and routine correspondence regarding the Bryn Mawr School, Hudson Shore Labor School and the Southern School for Workers.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5225: ALES Records 5225 C: ALES Course Materials 5225 E: ALES Labor Education Records 5225 I: ALES International Labor Records 5225 I: ALES International Labor Records 5577: U.S. Department of Commerce Bureau of the Census 1968 National Longitudinal Survey of Work Experience of Females, 14- 24 5657: American Labor Education Service Additional Documents 6046: Archives Union File (AUF)
Adult education of women. United States.; Adult education. United States. Curricula.; Federal aid to adult education. United States.; Labor unions and communism. United States.; Occupational training. United States.; Workers' education. United States.; Adult education teachers.; Aaron, Maxine L.; Affiliated Summer Schools for Workers.; American Labor Education Service (ALES); Bryn Mawr College; Bryn Mawr Summer School.; Hudson Shore Labor School.; Southern School for Workers.; United States. Works Progress Administration for Pennsylvania.; United States. Works Progress Administration for Pennsylvania. Educational and Recreational Division.; United States. Works Progress Administration. Workers' Education Advisory Committee.; United States. Works Progress Administration. Workers' Education Project.; Workers' Education Advisory Committee of Allegheny County.
3336743
- Affiliated School for Workers. ALES (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 1: Workers Education and the Trade Union Movement, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Author: Affiliated Schools for Workers
    Notes: Conference of Teachers in Workers Education, February 19-20, 1938
    Format: Publication
    Language: English.
  - Item 2: The Affiliated Schools for Workers (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Author: Eleanor G. Coit; Andria Taylor Hourwich
    Notes: Reprinted from Bulletin 8 of the World Association for Adult Education
  - Item 3: Labor Problems in Modern Society, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Author: Paul H. Douglas; William A. Orton
    Notes: Amherst College Classes for Workers, 1924-1925
  - Item 4: Summer School for Office Workers, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Author: Elinor Pancoast
    Notes: Reprinted from American Federationist, October, 1936
  - Item 5: The Affiliated Schools for Workers (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 6: Affiliated Schoolss Scrapbook, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: v.1:no.3/4 (1937:Mar.) Snapshots of Workers' Education Here and Abroad
  - Item 7: Summer School for Office Workers (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Leaflet
  - Item 8: Place of the White Collar Worker in the Labor Movement, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Philadelphia Conference, February 12-13, 1938. Leaflet
  - Item 9: Endowing Workers' Education (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 10: Endowing Workers' Education (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Copy 2.
  - Item 11: Government Support of Worker's Education: With Special Reference to Denmark and Sweden (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Author: Eleanor G. Coit
- Affiliated School for Workers. Reading Lists (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 1: Suggested Reading List: Novels, Plays, Giographies, Poetry Dealing With Social and Economic Problems, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author: Continuation Committee
    Notes: May, 1933.
  - Item 2: Suggested Reading List: Novels, Plays, Giographies, Poetry Dealing With Social and Economic Problems, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author: Elinore G. Black
  - Item 3: Second Supplement to the Annotated List of Pamphlet Material for Workers' Classes, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author: Orlie Pell
  - Item 4: Annoted List of Materials for Workers' Classes, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: January, 1932.
- Affiliated School for Workers. Court Materials (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 1: The Shrinking Week and the Growing Wage: Present Problems in the Light of the Past, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Katherine H. Pollak; Dorothy Lefferts Moore
    Notes: Second edition
  - Item 2: The Shrinking Week and the Growing Wage: Present Problems in the Light of the Past, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notes: Third edtion
  - Item 3: A Study of the Activities of Former Students of the Summer Schools for Workers (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Louise Leonard McLaren; Olga Law Plunder
  - Item 4: This America: A Study of Literature Interpreting the Development of American Civilization, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Jean Carter
  - Item 5: Education That Changes Lives (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 6: Survey of Women in the Development of America (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 7: Monograph on Methods of Teaching English to Workers' Classes, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Olga Law Plunder
- Bryn Mawr Summer School for Woman Works in Industry (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Item 1: These Are The Words We Said, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Author: Hudson Shore Labor School
    Notes: Year book
  - Item 2: Keep Coming On, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Hudson Shore Labor School, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 1: Hudson Shore Year Book, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 2: 44 at Hudson Shore, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Item 3: 25th Summer Session for Men and Women Workers in Industry, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notes: June 30 - August 11, 1945.
- Hudson Shore Labor School, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 1: Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Author: Southern Summer School
  - Item 2: Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Item 3: Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Notes: Copy 3.
  - Item 4: Southern Summer School for Women Workers in Industry, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Notes: July 21 - September 1, 1938, Asheville, NC
- Southern Summer School for Women Workers (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Item 1: Report of the Barnard Summer School for Women Workers in Industry, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Author: Barnard Summer School
- Wisconsin Summer School for Workers in Industry (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 1: Six Weeks of University Life Offered You, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Author: Summer School for Workers in Industry
    Notes: July 2 to August 9, 1929
  - Item 2: Six Weeks of University Life Offered You, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Notes: June 28 to August 8, 1930
  - Item 3: Summer School for Workers in Industry, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Notes: June 27 to August 7, 1931
  - Item 4: The School for Workers, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Notes: June 26 - August 5, 1938
  - Item 5: The School for Workers, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Notes: June 26 - August 5, 1938. Copy 2.
  - Item 6: The School for Workers, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Item 7: Summer School for Workers in Industry: The Open Door to Wider Horizons (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Pittsburgh Committee. Minutes & Reports (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pittsburgh Committee. Correspondences (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Pittsburgh Committee. Treasurer (Box 1, Folder 11)
- WPA (Box 1, Folder 12)
- WPA Clippings (Box 1, Folder 13)